FILIPE R. R. OLIVEIRA frroliveira.github.io

Quick learner with diverse experience of technologies and programming languages. Eager for problem solving from product design, to systems architecture, application development, and lifecycle management. Strong background in mathematics. Always looking forward to collaborate with good ideas and people.

SKILLS

strong Scala, Java, C/C++

able to use C#, Android, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, SQL, Swift, Kotlin, Python, PHP, iOS, Objective-C, Go

tools Git, Jenkins, Splunk, Datadog, Grafana, Firebase

concepts Data Structures, Algorithms, Databases, Event-Driven, Functional

EXPERIENCE

Mobile Puzzle Game Creator Sep 2018 - Current

Design of original game concept and seamless player experience. Monetization through advertising and in-app purchases. Implementation for Android and iOS in C++ using the Cocos2d-X engine. Integration with Firebase for analytics, crash reporting, and remote configuration. Available soon.

HomeAway Software Engineer

Feb 2017 - Jun 2018

Backend applications in Scala that deliver marketing feeds to Google, Facebook and Criteo supported by Kafka, Cassandra, S3 and Spark. Continuous integration with Jenkins and continuous deployment with internal tool. Application monitoring and alerting with Datadog and Splunk.

Net-A-Porter Group Associate Developer

Nov 2015 - Feb 2017

Development, maintenance and support of REST services and payment APIs using Spring and Hibernate. Design of a ElasticSearch index. Pipeline configuration using Puppet. Prototype of a functional approach to API development with Java 8. Prototype of model-driven GraphQL implementation.

Critical Manufacturing Summer Internship

Jul - Sep 2014

WPF application in C# that compares and exports data between a staging environment and production. It used flexible and efficient Data Structures to accommodate a configurable data model, configurable behavior (through Runtime Reflection), and large amounts of data.

PROJECTS

Metamorphic Framework github.com/frroliveira/metamorphic

Mar - Jun 2015

Model-driven REST framework in Scala developed during master's dissertation. It uses an internal DSL for modeling applications that are generated with Macros. Performs better, in most cases, than common model-driven REST frameworks (LoopBack, Sails, Django REST), using Spray and Slick.

Others 2013 - 2017

- Web application in Python for GCP. Finalist of the 'Google Cloud Developer Challenge'. gcdc2013-studies.appspot.com
- Web development in PHP adopting responsive web design. vistuk.pt and spiracol.com
- Contribution to Scala open source project. github.com/typelevel/cats
- SQLite parser for Java using JavaCC. github.com/frroliveira/sqlipa

Academic 2013 - 2015

- Web application for the elderly in .NET and AngularJS. Integrates with: Google Sign In, Calendar, and Contacts.
- 2 native Android applications that implement: local database, data synchronization, QR codes, and NFC.
- 3 cross-platform games in C++ developed with Cocos2d-X: 1 using AdMob, and 2 using a physics engine.

COURSES

- Big Data Analysis with Scala and Spark Coursera 2018

- Functional Programming Design in Scala Coursera 2017

- Functional Programming Principles in Scala Coursera 2016

EDUCATION

Master in Informatics and Computing Engineering

2010 - 2015

Faculty of Engineering of the University of Porto, Portugal

thesis Exploring the Scala Macro System for Compile Time Model-Based Generation of Statically Type-Safe REST Services

ACHIEVEMENTS

INFORMATICS

- Finalist of the 'Google Cloud Developer Challenge', Google Online, 2013.
- 2nd in 'Agile Marathon for E-Commerce' (with team Agile Runners), Sonae / CiPS / FEUP, 2013.
- 9th in 'Ninja Challenge', AuditMark Online, 2013.

MATH

- 'New Talents in Mathematics' fellowship, Calouste Gulbenkian Foundation, 2011/2012.
- Winner at the 'MAT12' competition, University of Aveiro, 2008 & 2009.
- Bronze Medal at the 25th Portuguese Mathematical Olympiad, Lisbon, 2007.

OTHER

- Merit fellowship, University of Porto, 2013 & 2015. Regarding 2010/2011 & 2011/2012.
- 'Prémio Incentivo' award, University of Porto, 2012. Regarding 2010/2011.
- 'Prémio de Valor' award, Oliveira Júnior Basic and Secondary School, 2010.
- 4th at the Portuguese 'F1 in Schools' Final, Porto, 2010.

updated on April 2, 2019

short version